Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be looking
at lipids and specifically base
hydrolysis, which that's all
about saponification, meaning that
we're going to be making soap.
So how does this work?
Well, if you have a lipid or a fat
that you have from, maybe like the
store or from different animals
or all, all kinds of different
products, You can turn it into soap.
Now, how exactly does that work?
Well, let's say if I had a
triacylglycerol just like the one here.
This is what we refer
to as a fat or an oil.
So, just like vegetable oil or butter
or different fats that you find on meat.
That's kind of the same general idea.
Now, if you add a strong base to
it, so let's say lye for example,
or sodium hydroxide, or potassium
hydroxide, and you're to add those
under very, very intense heating
conditions, you can break it apart,
kind of like what your body does.
Your body puts it through acidic
conditions and breaks it apart.
But this we want to do through basic.
So when that happens, you're
going to make glycerol.
In this case, the fatty acid is going
to become a salt of the fatty acid.
So pontification, just to kind
of do the official definition, is
when a fat is heated under basic
conditions to create glycerol.
And the salts.
Now the cool thing about this is this
is how all the different salts are
formed that you can find in your house.
So from, for example, if you have a bar of
soap laying at maybe the sink, in a sink
or in your shower, that was essentially
made by adding sodium hydroxide or lye
to that, which that was originally a
saturated fat, so all single bonds.
And that's used to make a hard soap.
So if you have any of the ones that are
shaped like different things, That's
because it was a hard, a hard soap or
saturated because it was originally more
of a solid before it was being added.
Now, if we add a little bit of a weaker
base, slightly weaker, like KOH, and
if this is added to an unsaturated
fat, this is how you make liquid soap.
So like what you find, um,
maybe by your dishwasher or
potentially like your shampoos and
conditioners and things like that.
So like, for example, if you have like
a coconut shampoo or, or sometimes they
have avocado shampoos now, all those
are from oils that are unsaturated.
So that's a little bit of a fact.
Now, how does this reaction work?
Well, the whole idea is, let's say if
I have this particular triacylglycerol,
what you're going to be doing is breaking
apart by adding three moles of NaOH
under heat, just like I said before.
And the whole idea with this is
that, well, we're going to break
it into its different fragments.
So, if we copy and paste this down below,
we're going to be cutting it with our
little water scissors, just like how we
did with our previous hydrolysis video.
But the only difference here is, so if I
were to cut it, where is it weakest at?
Well, it is weakest right where the ester
bond is for all of these structures.
So we are going to cut it right at
this carbon oxygen bond because the
oxygens are pooling in both directions.
So it's ready to be broken under the
right conditions and basic is just right.
So when that happens, right, we're going
to be pooling that into its two pieces.
And now when that pulls, well, one side
is going to be our H from our NaOH, right?
So if we kind of like look at this
structure and think NaOH, I like to
think of this, this isn't completely
the right organikey way or, or
mechanism way, but it makes it easy to
remember is that with this one, we're
going to have two fragments, right?
There's H.
and then NaO minus Na plus.
So we have two charges on this.
Maybe we'll use a different color here.
So with each of these, so once I release,
erase the purple or erase the little x's
here, just like so, we're going to put our
salt compound, because this is going to be
a fatty acid salt on the right hand side.
So we have our O minus and Na plus on
each of these different structures.
So Na plus, O minus, Na so this is a
fatty acid salt, okay, which just as
a reminder for if you don't remember
you're organic, this is also known as
a carboxylate, okay, so it has an A T E
ending to refer to the salt form, now the
other product is a glycerol that forms.
And these are your two different
products in your final reaction.
Okay?
So, when we look at the complete reaction
just like so, you're going to have your,
your big fatty acid, and it gets split
into the fatty acid salt and glycerol.
I hope this video helped.
Thank you so much for watching, please
hit that like and subscribe button, and
I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now.